James M. Vicary Papers 1998.0320
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
James M. Vicary Papers
undated, 1936-1967.
1998.0320
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
5.2 Linear feet
James McDonald Vicary was born in Detroit 30 April 1915. He has been associated with the J.L. Hudson Company (Detroit), Benson and Benson (Princeton, NJ), Crowell-Collier Publications Company (NY), and Benton and Bowles, Inc. (NY). Mr. Vicary is the author of articles on research in such journals as the Public Opinion Quarterly, Harvard Business Review, and Printer's Ink. Mr. Vicary is most known for his work with subliminal messages in advertising.
Vicary, James M.
Biography
James McDonald Vicary was born in Detroit, MI, on 30 April 1915. He received his A.B. degree from the University of Michigan in 1940. While at University, Vicary ran the Bureau of Student Opinion. He has been associated with the J.L. Hudson Company ( Detroit, MI), Benson and Benson ( Princeton, NJ), Crowell-Collier Publications Company (NY), and Benton and Bowles, Inc. (NY). He was a member of the American Association for Public Opinion Research, American Psychological Association, American Sociological Society, American Statistical Association, Society for Applied Anthropology and American Marketing Association. Mr. Vicary is the author of articles on research in such journals as the Public Opinion Quarterly, Harvard Business Review, and Printer's Ink
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, publications, surveys, and related materials pertaining to Mr. Vicary's survey research and polling activities. The majority of the materials date from 1948-1959.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal Materials ( undated, 1940s-1967 )
Series II: James M. Vicary Company ( undated, 1936-1967 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to public polling and survey research. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Separated Materials
The following titles have been cataloged: Madison Avenue USA Dodd The Hidden Persuaders Dodd Public Relations Dodd Motivation research in advertising & marketing Dodd Die Geheimsymbole der Alchymie, Arzneikunde und Astrologie des Mittelalters Dodd Symbol and metaphor Dodd
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Public opinion polls.; Public opinion--United States.; Publications.; Social sciences--Research.; Social surveys--Methodology.; Surveys (documents).
- Series I: Personal Materials, undated, 1940s-1967
  - Clippings, 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1940s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1964-1965, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lecture recording, undated (Box 1)
    Access
    The recording is in a format that is not supported for unmediated access.
  - Personal Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: James M. Vicary Company, undated, 1936-1959
  - Exhibits for Certification, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Index, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Index—Sourcebook volumes, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Index—Table of Contents vols. 1-14, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript materials for articles, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Studies assembled in California, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Subliminal Publicity, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Company Records
    - Vol. 2, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Vol. 3, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Vol. 4, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Vol. 5, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Vol. 6, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Vol. 7, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Vol. 8, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Vol. 9, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Vol. 10, 1946, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Vol. 11, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Vol. 12, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Vol. 13, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Vol. 14, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Vol. 15, 1936-1959 (Box 4, Folder 35)